Present our presentation by Representative
Cutler on the role of the state and how to
keep the feds out of our business. That'll
be later discussions.
My boss is here, Marvin Dodge. I hope that
joke didn't get me in trouble.
Oh.
You don't last long with a personality
like Maz do.
So this is going to be 10 minutes and then
we're actually going to do break out into
two breakouts before lunch. I'll give some
instructions after this for that.
Fantastic. Thank you. Thanks for putting
the break. I think the sound will work. –
I will see if the sound works. If not,
we'll bring our live demo team back up
here to help. So, I brought a couple of
friends with me to help. Let's see what
they have to say. And the sound did not
work.
Is your sound up? It's going to be off.
It was muted though.
One more try. Welcome to Utah, folks.
Digital identity is fabulous. It's really
great. You're going to want one.
What is the state's
role
in digital identity? Wait, am I not in
charge of all the digital identity around
here?
If you see him, tell him he is in charge.
That'll be just fine. We've all seen lots
of evidence of the challenges with digital
identity, the breaches that are happening
around the world, often with governments
involved in these and And let's talk about
what the role of the state is compared to
the role of the federal government or the
role of private industry. And I would
suggest to you that the role of the state,
as we have heard so many times, is not to
control or to create but to endorse. And
the reason it's important for the state to
be involved is a matter of trust. In our
society, some of our largest tech
companies have lost the trust. and the
trust needs to come back to the
individual. And as Phil Windley presented,
put the individual back in control. So
let's try this again on what the state's
role is. Look, this is important. The role
of the state is to endorse, verify,
authenticate, protect, and guarantee an
individual's digital identity. This is
even more important. Personally, I really
like control. But the role of the state is
not to own, create, control, gatekeep, or
surveil an individual's digital identity.
– In the age of AI, even a legislator can
create terrible videos that could fool
somebody who's not paying attention. I
think we understand the points there.
Historically, the state has had a
significant role in identity. Often we
think of, oh, well, you know, the feds
have a passport, the feds provide a social
security number. But this goes back to the
presentation before. The root of the
identity is typically a state-endorsed
credential. We often start with a birth
certificate that in most cases is issued
by a state. And the state handles most of
the vital records. They're often used by
others in private industry or by the feds,
but the vital records is primarily a state
responsibility.
This was mentioned earlier, but I think
this is really important in the crux of
our argument for a state endorsed digital
identity. In the tech world where many of
us live, there is often a call for
expediency and for efficiency. It's more
efficient to use this or it's easier to
adopt VHS than beta. It's easier to adopt
or some people believe you know they like
the Android interface or the iPhone or iOS
interface. If we start with efficiency as
our value, then we will get a completely
different set of products than if we value
protection, security, and privacy. I think
if there's anything we've learned over the
past few years, and when we think about
social media, we think about online fraud,
is that we have to be more purposeful in
designing our identity systems and in the
systems that are going to be used by
millions and millions of people. Because
if we make a mistake, that mistake scales
again and again. So our argument is to
think carefully about your values. What
are your values as a state? What are your
values as an individual? Do we put our
rights protecting our children at the top
of our list? Many people would argue that
in designing social media, child
protection was not the top value. And over
the years we've had to pay a price for
that as things have changed and that
because that wasn't the most important
value in designing these systems. Our
argument is that we should protect the
vulnerable. You've all read the articles
of people, vulnerable adults, vulnerable
children getting scammed by people. We
heard a heartbreaking story today of what
can happen when a bad actor takes
advantage of somebody. We must look at our
values and put our most important personal
values, our most important moral values at
the top of the list and not let
efficiency, interoperability, or profit
take over the design of our identity
systems.
Those of you in the world of designing
systems understand that we have to think
big and we have to consider a lot of
different elements in our governance
framework. We've got to consider how are
we going to audit these systems? What are
the open protocols? Because historically,
we have to agree on a protocol and a
standard to to get mass adoption. We have
to think about how will this be enforced?
We saw an example just a minute. Okay, if
the enforcement and the verifier is so
ubiquitous that it can be put on a mobile
app, that'll reduce the cost to install
readers in all of our places. Should we
have a right to paper? That's going to be
a debate that I think many of us will
experience. Our friends in the UK have
said everybody gets a digital identity. We
have some people who don't want a digital
identity. How do we help them move forward
when 95% or 99% of the world is moving to
digital transactions? Can we build
transparency into the system so we can
identify fraud? Will we prevent all fraud?
You of all people know that preventing all
fraud is impossible, but can we make the
systems transparent so that we can
identify that fraud earlier and quicker so
we can take steps to reduce that fraud as
we go forward. Okay. Last I'll leave you
with this thought is that comparing the
state controlled identity which we've been
talking about and certainly we have some
examples of that in other countries
compared to a user controlled or a liberty
-based model. And we discussed many of
those key elements. Selective disclosure.
One issue we haven't talked a lot about
but is really important as we think big is
the guardianship. We've seen the
importance of guardianship in social
media. Should a parent be able to control
what apps a youth has access to? With
vulnerable adults, how do we design
systems to take into account that there
are going to be adults in our lives that
we have guardianships over or youth and
we've got to have that as a key mechanism
to have a guardianship capability. So
those are the key things that I wanted to
present to you.
It's been mentioned by my good friend
Senator that if we leave this up to the
federal government, we're going to be
stuck in Maya.
We're not moving forward. If we leave it
to our friends in industry, their
hierarchy of values is different. They
have fiduciary responsibility to make
money. And in some cases, they will view
making money as more important or
interoperability as more important than
protecting the vulnerable and protecting
individual rights. It is our
responsibility to exert
our constitutional and moral principles of
liberty, self-determination, and
individual autonomy. Thank you for coming
and for participating in this. And I think
we're moving to the break.